Finding Aid for Louis Sands Salt and Lumber Company (Manistee, Mich.) records, 1863-1932
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Louis Sands Salt and Lumber Company (Manistee, Mich.) records
1863-1932
Louis Sands Salt and Lumber Company (Manistee, Mich.)
851810 Bb. 2
Manistee, Michigan business firm; financial records, letterpress books, time books, and other records detailing to various business activities.
7.5 linear feet
30 microfilms
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was the gift of Mrs. Lottie B. Smith (donor no. 2335 ) and came to the library in September 1947.
The record group is open to research.
The Sands Salt and Lumber Company was one of the largest lumbering concerns in Manistee, Michigan. The firm was founded by Louis Sands, a Swede who was born on July 2, 1826,and who immigrated to the United States as a young man. After spending time in Boston and Chicago, Sands came to Manistee around 1853.
Between 1853 and 1856, Sands worked as a lumberjack. In 1856, he engaged in his first entrepreneurial venture, signing a contract to log another man's property. By 1864, Sands had saved enough money to buy an interest in a saw mill, and in 1870 he purchased for himself a small saw mill located in Eastlake.
Sands business prospered. In 1878, he became the owner of the bankrupt Tyron, Sweet & Co. Saw Mill, then the largest in the city. Located at the head of the Manistee River, it was equipped with the finest machinery available. In 1879, Sands sold the Eastlake Mill to R.G. Peters, and concentrated his energy on the former Tyron mill.
Sands continually expanded the base of his business operations. In 1889, he made a major purchase of timber land from the Grand Rapids and Indiana Railroad; and to exploit it he built both a harrow gauge railroad and a saw mill at Lake City. After removing more than 100,000,000 board feet from the area, Sands moved both railroad and mill to a new location, the former site of the Reitz mill on Manistee Lake. The Reitz operation Sands established was large, including the saw mill, a cooper shop, a machine shop, and two salt mills.
Sands was also involved with a variety of other business activities. Some of these, such as salt production and the operation of several ships, were closely associated with Sands lumbering operations. Others, such as the founding of Manistee's first electric power plant and a partnership in the banking firm of Sands & Burr, were less directly related to his primary concern of lumbering.
Louis Sands died August 24,1905, yet the company which he founded continued in existence for many years after his death.
The records of Louis Sands business interests have been arranged in seven series. These include letterpress books, journals, ledgers, time books, subsidiary volumes, associated records, and miscellaneous. The letterpress books and miscellaneous documents have been retained in their original format. The remaining material has been microfilmed.
The original relationship between much of the business records has been lost beyond reconstruction. Because of this, volumes have been grouped by type rather than by business venture. The loss of the original relationship between the volumes was responsible, as well, for the establishment of an arbitrary chronological order for some volumes.
All of the material microfilmed as well as a large quantity of material relating to Sands & Burr, bankers, which was not filmed, has been placed on permanent loan to the Manistee Historical Museum in Manistee.
Subjects:
Banks and banking--Michigan--Manistee.; Business records.; Logging--Michigan--Manistee.; Lumbering--Michigan--Manistee.; Manistee (Mich.); Salt industry and trade--Michigan--Manistee.; Sands, Louis, 1825-1905.; Sands and Burr (Bankers: Manistee, Mich.); Louis Sands Salt and Lumber Company (Manistee, Mich.); Manistee River Improvement Company (Manistee, Mich.)
- Letterpress books, 1901-1929
  There are two subseries of letterpress books. One, created through Sands banking activities, covers the years 1901-1929. The other subseries, correspondence of George M. Burr, trustee, is dated between 1902 and 1925. Both sets of letterpress books lack several volumes for the earliest years.
  - Sands and Burr, Bankers, 1901-1929
    - Vol. 7:, December 1901-August 1902 (Box 1)
      (Volumes nos. 1-6 were not received)
    - Vol. 8:, August 1902-June 1903 (Box 1)
    - Vol. 9:, June 1903-May 1904 (Box 1)
    - Vol. 10:, May 1904-August 1905 (Box 1)
    - Vol. 11:, August 1905-August 1906 (Box 1)
    - Vol. 12:, August 1906-August 1907 (Box 2)
    - Vol. 13:, August 1907-May 1908 (Box 2)
    - Vol. 14:, May 1908-March 1909 (Box 2)
    - Vol. 15:, March 1909-May 1910 (Box 2)
    - Vol. 16:, March 1910-March 1911 (Box 2)
    - Vol. 17:, March 1911-January 1912 (Box 2)
    - Vol. 18:, January 1912-September 1912 (Box 3)
    - Vol. 19:, September 1912-May 1913 (Box 3)
    - Vol. 20:, May 1913-April 1914 (Box 3)
    - Vol. 21:, April 1914-March 1915 (Box 3)
    - Vol. 22:, March 1915-April 1916 (Box 3)
    - Vol. 23:, April 1916-April 1917 (Box 4)
    - Vol. 24:, April 1917-March 1918 (Box 4)
    - Vol. 25:, March 1918-March 1919 (Box 4)
    - Vol. 26:, March 1919-February 1920 (Box 4)
    - Vol. 27:, February 1920-January 1921 (Box 4)
    - Vol. 28:, January 1921-March 1922 (Box 5)
    - Vol. 29:, March 1922-May 1923 (Box 5)
    - Vol. 30:, May 1923-September 1924 (Box 5)
    - Vol. 31:, September 1924-September 1929 (Box 5)
  - George M. Burr, Trustee, 1902-1925
    - Vol. 5:, August 1902-October 1903 (Box 5)
      (Vols. 1-4 were not received)
    - Vol. 6:, October 1903-January 1905 (Box 6)
    - Vol. 7:, January 1905-February 1906 (Box 6)
    - Vol. 8:, February 1906-August 1907 (Box 6)
    - Vol. 9:, August 1907-July 1909 (Box 6)
    - Vol. 10:, July 1909-October 1912 (Box 6)
    - Vol. 11:, October 1912-April 1915 (Box 7)
    - Vol. 12:, April 1915-December 1915 (Box 7)
    - Vol. 13:, December 1915-June 1918 (Box 7)
    - Vol. 14:, June 1918-September 1920 (Box 7)
    - Vol. 15:, September 1920-December 1922 (Box 7)
    - Vol. 16:, December 1922-June 1925 (Box 7)
- Miscellaneous
  - Louis Sands
    - Business journal, 1873-1874 (Box 8)
    - Bills, 1905-1908 (Box 8)
  - Sands and Burr
    - Correspondence with Michigan Trust Co., 1910-1929 (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
  - Manistee Improvement Co.
    - Annual reports, 1884-1900 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, 1884-1895 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, 1896-1900 (Box 8)
  - Petit Salt Co.
    - Miscellaneous records (Box 8)
- Journals, 1881-1925
  Most of the journals are from the Reitz plant, or its predecessor operations. A few journals, the purpose of which are unclear, have been arranged in chronological order.
  - Reitz Plant
    - March 1881-August 1883 (Box 9, Reel 1)
    - September 1883-February 1885 (Box 9, Reel 1)
    - March 1885-December 1887 (Box 9, Reel 1)
    - (cont.; beginning with August 1885), March 1885-December 1887 (Box 9, Reel 2)
    - January 1888-December 1890 (Box 9, Reel 2)
    - January 1891-December 1895 (Box 9, Reel 2)
    - (cont.; beginning with April 1891), January 1891-December 1895 (Box 9, Reel 3)
    - January 1896-November 1899 (Box 9, Reel 3)
    - December 1899-December 1901 (Box 9, Reel 4)
    - January 1902-December 1905 (Box 9, Reel 4)
    - (cont.; beginning with March 1905), January 1902-December 1905 (Box 9, Reel 5)
    - October 1898-December 1901 (Box 9, Reel 5)
  - Miscellaneous
    - April 1871-April 1879 (Box 9, Reel 5)
    - July 1881-April 1882 (Box 9, Reel 5)
    - May 1888-December 1898 (Box 9, Reel 5)
    - February 1891-November 1895 (Box 9, Reel 5)
    - December 1895-December 1897 (Box 9, Reel 6)
    - May 1904-December 1906 (Box 9, Reel 6)
    - April 1905-July 1925 (Box 9, Reel 6)
- Ledgers, 1871-1932
  Of the major record series, the ledgers are by far the most difficult to use. They have been divided into three groups, arbitrarily labeled 1, 2, and 3. The ledgers in groups 1 and 2 appear to be related to one another, but there is no indication as to what operations they were maintained for. Group 3 is a totally arbitrary arrangement of ledgers that did not appear to fit into either of the first two groups.
  - Group 1
    - April 1871-August 1876 (Box 9, Reel 6)
    - August 1876-March 1879 (Box 9, Reel 6)
    - (cont.), August 1876-March 1879 (Box 9, Reel 7)
    - April 1879-June 1883 (Box 9, Reel 7)
    - June 1883-March 1886 (Box 9, Reel 7)
    - June 1883-March 1886 (Box 9, Reel 8)
    - October 1888-February 1891 (Box 9, Reel 8)
    - February 1891-December 1894 (Box 9, Reel 8)
    - January 1895-November 1897 (Box 9, Reel 8)
    - (cont.), January 1895-November 1897 (Box 9, Reel 9)
  - Group 2
    - March 1881-February 1885 (Box 9, Reel 9)
    - March 1885-December 1887 (Box 9, Reel 9)
    - January 1888-December 1890 (Box 9, Reel 9)
    - (cont.), January 1888-December 1890 (Box 9, Reel 10)
    - January 1891-April 1895 (Box 9, Reel 10)
    - April 1895-December 1898 (Box 9, Reel 10)
    - (cont.), April 1895-December 1898 (Box 9, Reel 11)
    - January 1899-December 1901 (Box 9, Reel 11)
    - January 1902-April 1905 (Box 9, Reel 11)
    - (cont.), January 1902-April 1905 (Box 9, Reel 12)
    - April 1905-December 1909 (Box 9, Reel 12)
    - January 1910-December 1914 (Box 9, Reel 12)
    - (cont.), January 1910-December 1914 (Box 9, Reel 13)
    - January 1915-December 1919 (Box 9, Reel 13)
    - January 1920-March 1925 (Box 9, Reel 13)
    - (cont.), January 1920-March 1925 (Box 9, Reel 14)
    - April 1925-June 1932 (Box 9, Reel 14)
  - Group 3
    - November 1864-September 1866 (Box 9, Reel 14)
    - December 1873-October 1874 (Box 9, Reel 14)
    - April 1874-March 1878 (Box 9, Reel 14)
    - April 1875-May 1877 (Box 9, Reel 14)
    - January 1876-November 1876 (Box 9, Reel 15)
    - May 1879-May 1880 (Box 9, Reel 15)
    - July 1881-November 1883 (Box 9, Reel 15)
    - November 1883-April 1885 (Box 9, Reel 15)
    - November 1884-July 1888 (Box 9, Reel 15)
    - (cont.), November 1884-July 1888 (Box 9, Reel 16)
    - May 1885-September 1886 (Box 9, Reel 16)
    - June 1887-October 1888 (Box 9, Reel 16)
    - March 1891-December 1892 (Box 9, Reel 16)
    - (cont.), March 1891-December 1892 (Box 9, Reel 17)
    - April 1893-September 1894 (Box 9, Reel 17)
    - October 1898-December 1901 (Box 9, Reel 17)
    - January 1899-May 1909 (Box 9, Reel 17)
    - January 1901-October 1902 (Box 9, Reel 17)
    - February 1905-June 1909 (Box 9, Reel 17)
    - (cont.), February 1905-June 1909 (Box 9, Reel 18)
    - January 1906-March 1908 (Box 9, Reel 18)
    - May 1910-March 1913 (Box 9, Reel 18)
    - May 1923-November 1923 (Box 9, Reel 18)
- Time books, 1884-1930
  Like the journals, the source of most of the time books is identifiable. Of the two sets of time books, one comes from the "Third Ward Plant", and the other from the "Fourth Ward Plant". Sands' time books are of particular interest because his firm was a major employer of immigrant Swedes.
  - Third Ward Plant
    - July 1884-October 1888 (Box 9, Reel 18)
    - November 1888-December 1892 (Box 9, Reel 18)
    - (cont.; beginning with June 1889), November 1888-December 1892 (Box 9, Reel 19)
    - April 1893-September 1896 (Box 9, Reel 19)
    - October 1896-August 1899 (Box 9, Reel 19)
    - September 1899-October 1902 (Box 9, Reel 19)
    - November 1902-April 1906 (Box 9, Reel 20)
    - May 1906-February 1910 (Box 9, Reel 20)
    - (cont.; beginning with October 1908), May 1906-February 1910 (Box 9, Reel 21)
    - March 1910-July 1913 (Box 9, Reel 21)
  - Fourth Ward Plant
    - March 1891-April 1895 (Box 9, Reel 21)
    - May 1895-June 1897 (Box 9, Reel 21)
    - June 1898-October 1902 (Box 9, Reel 21)
    - November 1902-June 1906 (Box 9, Reel 21)
    - November 1902-June 1906 (cont.; beginning with August 1903 (Box 9, Reel 22)
    - July 1906-September 1910 (Box 9, Reel 22)
    - September 1910-July 1913 (Box 9, Reel 22)
  - Miscellaneous
    - January 1924-December 1926 (Box 9, Reel 22)
    - April 1928-October 1930 (Box 9, Reel 22)
- Subsidiary volumes, 1866-1925
  Subsidiary volumes contain record books which were related to a particular aspect of Sands business ventures, but which do not seem to be basic records of the firm. Among these volumes are the camp and mill scales records, the sales and purchases books, the salt production records and finally an inventory done for the receiver of the Louis Sands estate on March 20, 1925.
  - Camp and Mill Scales
    - (log book), January 1866-March 1867 (Box 9, Reel 23)
    - December 1880-August 1890 (Box 9, Reel 23)
    - November 1890-November 1898 (Box 9, Reel 23)
    - April 1899-November 1907 (Box 9, Reel 23)
    - May 1899-November 1907 (Box 9, Reel 23)
    - (cont.; beginning with June 1901), May 1899-November 1907 (Box 9, Reel 24)
    - January 1920-December 1923 (Box 9, Reel 24)
    - December 1921-September 1925 (Box 9, Reel 24)
  - Sales and Purchase Books
    - October 1875-October 1877 (Box 9, Reel 24)
    - September 1889-June 1897 (Box 9, Reel 24)
    - September 1899-July 1908 (Box 9, Reel 24)
    - (cont.; beginning with July 1900), September 1899-July 1908 (Box 9, Reel 25)
      [re-shot on reel 30]
    - August 1908-April 1916 (Box 9, Reel 25)
    - May 1916-September 1925 (Box 9, Reel 25)
    - (cont.; beginning February 1922), May 1916-September 1925 (Box 9, Reel 26)
  - Salt Records
    - December 1896-December 1904 (Box 9, Reel 26)
      (volume re-shot on reel 30)
    - January 1905-September 1912 (Box 9, Reel 26)
    - October 1912-May 1920 (Box 9, Reel 26)
    - June 1920-November 1925 (Box 9, Reel 26)
  - Inventory for Receiver of Louis Sands, March 20, 1925 (Box 9, Reel 26)
- Associated Records
  Associated records include volumes of firms which were independent of Sands but which somehow became interspersed with the Sands records. It is possible Sands held either a minor interest in these firms, purchased the assets of the firm and integrated it into his 6perations, or was greatly interested in the work of the firm. Such records tend to be fragmentary. Included are the Manistee River Improvement Co.; Sands and Rothschild; W.A. Waite, Filer, Tyson, & Co.; Wadsworth, Adams & Co. Engelmann, Babcock & Salling; and the Boom Co. of Manistee.
  - Manistee River Improvement Co.
    - Stock book, September 1870-September 1900 (Box 9, Reel 26)
    - Stock book (cont.), September 1870-December 1900 (Box 9, Reel 27)
    - Journal, September 1870-December 1900 (Box 9, Reel 27)
    - Ledger, September 1870-December 1900 (Box 9, Reel 27)
      (target in error; volume re-shot on reel 30)
  - Sands and Rothschild
    - Journal, January 1879-January 1881 (Box 9, Reel 27)
    - Ledger, January 1879-August 1880 (Box 9, Reel 27)
    - Ledger, January 1879-December 1880 (Box 9, Reel 27)
  - W.A. Waite
    - Ledger, May 1894-December 1901 (Box 9, Reel 27)
    - Ledger (cont.), May 1894-December 1901 (Box 9, Reel 28)
  - Filer, Tyson and Co.
    - Journal, June 1863-March 1866 (Box 9, Reel 28)
  - Wadsworth, Adams and Co.
    - Ledger, July 1868-December 1869 (Box 9, Reel 28)
  - Engelmann, Babcock and Salling
    - Sales, May 1873-September 1875 (Box 9, Reel 28)
    - Sales (cont.; beginning May 1875), May 1873-September 1875 (Box 9, Reel 29)
  - Boom Co., Manistee
    - Log Record, February 1896-December 1909 (Box 9, Reel 29)
  - W.A. Waite
    - Time book (?), May 1894-November 1898 (Box 9, Reel 29)
- Subsidiary and Associated Records
  (volumes re-shot for greater clarity)
  - Sales and Purchase book, September 1899-July 1908 (Box 9, Reel 30)
    (from reel 25)
  - Salt Record, December 1896-December 1904 (Box 9, Reel 30)
    (from reel 26)
  - Salt Record, January 1905-September 1912 (Box 9, Reel 30)
  - Manistee River Improvement Co., Journal, 1870-1900 (Box 9, Reel 30)
    (from reel 27)
  - Manistee River Improvement Co., Ledger, 1870-1900 (Box 9, Reel 30)